I've noticed that almost all the really good machine learning
我注意到 几乎所有真正优秀的机器学习者
practitioners tend to be very sophisticated in understanding of Bias and Variance.
对偏差(偏离度)和方差(集中度)的处理都是非常有经验的
Bias and Variance is one of those concepts that's easily learned but difficult to master.
偏差和方差的处理往往非常容易入门 但是非常难以精通
Even if you think you've seen the basic concepts of Bias and Variance,
即使你认为你已经看完了偏差和方差的基础理论
there's often more new ones to it than you'd expect.
也常常会发现总会有一些出乎你意料的东西
In the Deep Learning Area,
在深度学习领域
another trend is that there's been
另一个现象是有关
less discussion of what's called the bias-variance tradeoff.
偏差-方差权衡(也有叫做偏差-方差困境)的讨论很少
You might have heard this thing called the bias-variance tradeoff.
你可能之前已经听说过这个被称为“偏差-方差权衡”的东西
But in Deep Learning Area there's less of a tradeoff,
但是在深度学习领域 这不仅仅是两者间的权衡问题
so we'd still talk of the bias,
我们仍然讨论偏差
we still talk of the variance,
也仍然讨论方差
but we just talk less about the bias-variance tradeoff.
但是我们对偏差-方差权衡要讲的不多
Let's see what this means.
让我们一起来看看为什么这么说
Let's see the data set that looks like this.
大家应该看到了屏幕上这些训练集
If you fit a straight line to the data,
如果你用一条直线来区分样本数据
maybe get a logistic regression fit to that.
那么用逻辑回归可能画出图上的这条直线
This is not a very good fit to the data.
这和训练数据的拟合度并不高
And so this is class of a high bias,
这样的分类我们称之为高偏差
what we say that this is underfitting the data.
或者换一种说法 这是欠拟合
On the opposite end,
相对的
if you fit an incredibly complex classifier,
如果你使用一个极为复杂的分类器
maybe deep neural network,
例如深度神经网络
or neural network with all the hidden units,
或者含有所有隐藏神经元的神经网络
maybe you can fit the data perfectly,
或许你可以像图上画的这样完美区分训练数据
but that doesn't look like a great fit either.
但那看上去也并不是一个非常好的分类算法
So there's a classifier of high variance and this is overfitting the data.
这个高方差的分类器 我们也称之为过拟合
And there might be some classifier in between,
在这两种分类器之间
with a medium level of complexity,
我们应该能找到一种不那么复杂的
that maybe fits it correctly like that.
但是能正确分类的算法 像图上这样
That looks like a much more reasonable fit to the data,
这看起来对数据的区分非常合理
so we call that just right. It's somewhere in between.
我们认为这才是完美匹配的算法 结果居于欠拟合与过拟合之间
So in a 2D example like this,
像图上的这个有两个特征值
with just two features,
的2D样例
X-1 and X-2, you can plot the data and visualize bias and variance.
我们把横轴标为x1 纵轴标为x2 你可以绘制数据 把偏差和方差可视化
In high dimensional problems,
在高维度问题中
you can't plot the data and visualize division boundary.
你无法将数据绘制在图上 并在图上进行区分
Instead, there are couple of different metrics,
然而 对应这样的情况也会有几个不同的方法
that we'll look at, to try to understand bias and variance.
让我们来探讨一下 试着去理解偏差和方差的含义
So continuing our example of cat picture classification,
让我们接着讲猫的图片分类的例子
where that's a positive example and that's a negative example,
这里有一个正确的样本和一个错误的样本
the two key numbers to look at and understand bias and variance will be
理解偏差和方差的两个关键数据是
the train set error and the dev set or the development set error.
训练集误差和开发集误差
So for the sake of argument,
为了便于讨论
let's say that you're recognizing cats in pictures,
我们假设你已经在图片中识别出了猫
is something that people can do nearly perfectly, right?
这几乎每个人都能完美做到的 对吧
So let's say, your training set error is 1% and your dev set error is,
所以我们可以理解为 你的训练集误差是1% 而对于开发集误差
for the sake of argument,
为了便于讨论
let's say is 11%.
我们假设是11%
So in this example,
在这个例子中
you're doing very well on the training set,
你的模型对训练集处理得非常好
but you're doing relatively poorly on the development set.
但是相对来说 开发集处理得就有些不尽如人意
So this looks like you might have overfit the training set,
所以这可能是在处理训练集时过拟合了
that somehow you're not generalizing well,
意味着该算法应用到开发集中的所有需要交叉验证的
to this whole cross-validation set in the development set.
数据时 并未处理得十分妥当
And so if you have an example like this,
如果你得到的结果和这个例子一样
we would say this has high variance.
我们将它定义成高方差
So by looking at the training set error and the development set error,
通过观察训练集误差和开发集误差
you would be able to render a diagnosis of your algorithm having high variance.
你将能判断出你的模型算法是否有高方差的问题
Now, let's say, that you measure your training set and your dev set error,
现在让我们再来看第二个例子 假设你得到了训练集和开发集的误差
and you get a different result.
有了与第一个例子不一样的结果
Let's say, that your training set error is 15%.
假设训练集的误差是15%
I'm writing your training set error in the top row,
我把这个训练集误差写在第一行
and your dev set error is 16%.
假设你的开发集误差是16%
In this case, assuming that humans achieve roughly 0% error,
在这种情况下 我们假设人工识别误差是0%
that humans can look at these pictures and just tell if it's cat or not,
因为人可以直接看到这些图片 并判断出这是否是一只猫
then it looks like the algorithm is not even doing very well on the training set.
所以看上去 这个算法在训练集上的表现并不尽如人意
So if it's not even fitting the training data seam that well,
如果它并未将训练集数据处理得很好
then this is underfitting the data.
这就是欠拟合
And so this algorithm has high bias.
我们认为这个算法是高偏差的
But in contrast, this actually generalizing at a reasonable level to the dev set,
但相比之下 这个算法应用在开发集时还处于一个可接受的水准
whereas performance in the dev set is only 1% worse than performance in the training set.
和应用在训练集时的表现相比 误差只多了1%
So this algorithm has a problem of high bias,
所以这个算法的问题是高偏差
because it was not even fitting the training set.
因为它并不能在训练集上对样本进行很好的识别
Well, this is similar to the leftmost plots we had on the previous slide.
这种情况和我们在上一页PPT中最左边的图极为相似
Now, here's another example.
接下来让我们来讲另一个例子
Let's say that you have 15% training set error,
假设你的算法在训练集上的误差是15%
so that's pretty high bias,
这是相当高的偏差
but when you evaluate to the dev set it does even worse,
但当你将该算法应用在开发集时 情况变得更糟
maybe it does 30%.
可能有30%的误差
In this case, I would diagnose this algorithm as having high bias,
在这种情况下 我可以判断出这个算法是高偏差的
because it's not doing that well on the training set, and high variance.
它并没有将训练集处理好 并且还是高方差的
So this has really the worst of both worlds.
这是一种非常 十分 极其糟糕的算法
And one last example,
让我们看看最后一个例子
if you have 0.5 training set error,
假设你有0.5%的训练集误差
and 1% dev set error,
以及1%的开发集误差
then maybe our users are quite happy,
这是让大家都喜闻乐见的算法
that you have a cat classifier with only 1% error,
对猫的分类仅有1%的误差
then just we have low bias and low variance.
所以这个算法是低偏差和低方差的
One subtlety, that I'll just briefly mention that
有一点要注意 我简单地提一下
we'll leave to a later video to discuss in detail,
我们会在之后的视频教程中详细讨论
is that this analysis is predicated on the assumption,
这种分析方法的前提基于真人识别的
that human level performance gets nearly 0% error or,
误差为0%的假设
more generally, that the optimal error,
一般来说 我们称之为理想误差
sometimes called base error,
或者有时我们叫它基本误差
so the base in optimal error is nearly 0%.
基本误差接近0%
I don't want to go into detail on this in this particular video,
在这期视频中我就不展开来说这个问题了
but it turns out that if the optimal error or the base error were much higher, say,
但是如果理想误差或基本误差比较高 假设
it were 15%, then if you look at this classifier,
是15% 那么如果我们继续来看这个分类算法
15% is actually perfectly reasonable for training set and you
15%误差实际上对训练集来说是一个近乎完美的结果了
wouldn't see it as high bias and also a pretty low variance.
你不应该认为它是高偏差的 低方差的算法
So the case of how to analyze bias and variance,
所以如何来分析偏差和方差
when no classifier can do very well, for example,
如果没有分类算法能做好 假设
if you have really blurry images,
如果真的有模糊图像
so that even a human or just no system could possibly do very well,
哪怕是真人或者任何系统都不能进行分类
then maybe base error is much higher,
那基本误差就会非常高
and then there are some details of how this analysis will change.
然后会有一些不同的手段来改变分析方法
But leaving aside this subtlety for now,
但是我们现在先不讨论这个问题
the takeaway is that by looking at
而我们可以发现 通过观察
your training set error you can get a sense of how well you are fitting,
训练集的误差 可以知道你的算法是否至少可以将
at least the training data,
训练集数据处理得很好
and so that tells you if you have a bias problem.
然后总结出是否属于高偏差问题
And then looking at how much higher your error goes,
然后通过观察同一个算法
when you go from the training set to the dev set,
在开发集上的误差提高了多少
that should give you a sense of how bad is the variance problem,
可以知道这个算法是否有高方差问题
so you'll be doing a good job generalizing from a training set to the dev set,
这样你可以很好地把算法从训练集应用至开发集
that gives you sense of your variance.
这会让你意识到方差问题
All this is under the assumption that the base error is quite
上述结果都基于基本误差非常低并且
small and that your training and your dev sets are drawn from the same distribution.
你的训练集和开发集都来自同一个分布的假设
If those assumptions are violated,
如果不满足这些假设
there's a more sophisticated analysis you could do,
那么你需要做一个更复杂的分析
which we'll talk about in the later video.
我们将在之后几期视频教程中讨论
Now, on the previous slide,
好了 在上一张PPT中
you saw what high bias,
我们展示了高偏差
high variance looks like,
和高方差的形态
and I guess you have the sense of what it a good class can look like.
我猜你已经意识到一个优秀的分类器看上去是什么样的了
What does high bias and high variance looks like?
高偏差和高方差的算法看上去如何呢
This is kind of the worst of both worlds.
这是一种无比糟糕的情况
So you remember, we said that a classifier like this,
你应该还记得 我们说过一个像这样的分类器
then your classifier has high bias,
这意味着你的算法是高偏差的
because it underfits the data.
因为欠拟合
So this would be a classifier that is mostly linear and therefore underfits the data,
所以可以说 由于这几乎是个线性分类器(直线) 所以它欠拟合了
we're drawing this is purple.
我们用紫色来标一下
But if somehow your classifier does some weird things,
但是如果在某些情况下你的分类器做了些诡异的事情(像我现在画的这样)
then it is actually overfitting parts of the data as well.
那么实际上这部分属于过拟合了
So the classifier that I drew in purple,
所以我在紫色部分标示的分类器
has both high bias and high variance.
同时具有高偏差和高方差的问题
Where it has high bias, because,
从图上看 这里有高偏差问题
by being a mostly linear classifier,
几乎是一个线性分类器
is just not fitting.
无法拟合分类
You know, this quadratic line shape that well,
你看 就像图上这个曲线形状的类别
but by having too much flexibility in the middle,
但是这个分类器中间 又变得十分扭曲
it somehow gets this example,
它虽然诡异地正确区分了这个叉样本
and this example. Overfits those two examples as well.
和这个圈样本 但这显然就属于过拟合了
So this classifier kind of has high bias because it was mostly linear,
综上所述 我们称这个分类器是高偏差的 因为它几乎是直线
but you need maybe a curve function or quadratic function.
但你需要的可能是一个曲线函数或二次函数
And it has high variance,
同时它也是高方差的
because it had too much flexibility to fit those two mislabel,
因为它在中间用极为扭曲的算法 对两个孤立的
or those live examples in the middle as well.
甚至可能是错误的样本进行了拟合
In case this seems contrived, well,
看上去这比较像人为的
this example is a little bit contrived in two dimensions,
这个样例在二维中看上去不太自然
but with very high dimensional inputs.
但是当你有相当高维度的输入特征
You actually do get things with
你可能在获取特征的过程中
high bias in some regions and high variance in some regions,
在一些地方遇到了高偏差的问题 一些地方遇到了高方差的问题
and so it is possible to get classifiers like this
所以很可能最终得到了在高维度特征输入情况下
in high dimensional inputs that seem less contrived.
产生了这样不自然的分类
So to summarize, you've seen how by looking at your algorithm's error on
让我们总结一下 这节课我们学习了如何通过观察算法
the training set and your algorithm's error on the dev set you can try to diagnose,
在训练集和开发集的误差来诊断
whether it has problems of high bias or high variance,
它是否有高偏差或者高方差的问题
or maybe both, or maybe neither.
或许两者都有 或许都没有
And depending on whether your algorithm suffers from bias or variance,
基于算法遇到高偏差或高方差问题的不同情况
it turns out that there are different things you could try.
我们可以尝试不同的方法来进行改进
So in the next video, I want to present to you,
所以在下一个视频教程中 我希望能给你介绍一种方法
what I call a basic recipe for Machine Learning,
我称之为机器学习的基本准则
that lets you more systematically try to improve your algorithm,
那会让你在遇到高偏差或者高方差问题时
depending on whether it has high bias or high variance issues.
能够更系统地去尝试改进你的算法
So let's go on to the next video.
让我们继续下一期教程